世间有两种人
There are two kinds of folks
总在思考如何杀人
who sit around thinking about how to kill people:
精神病患者和侦探小说作家
psychopaths and mystery writers.
我属于高收入的后者  我是谁
I'm the kind that pays better. Who am I?
我是里克・卡塞尔
I'm Rick Castle.
卡塞尔
Castle.
我浑身都散发着粗犷美  是不是
I really am ruggedly handsome, aren't I?
每位作家都离不开灵感
Every writer needs inspiration.
-我的灵感已经找到了  -凯特・贝克特探长
- And I found mine. - Detective Kate Beckett.
贝克特
Beckett.
-妮基・希特  -那个角色是以你为原型
- Nikki Heat? - The character he's basing on you.
很庆幸我和市长是朋友
And thanks to my friendship with the mayor,
她办案我能跟着
I get to be on her case.
要是你能打我  我会很开心
I would be happy to let you spank me.
我们一起抓过凶手
And together, we catch killers.
我们俩可是最佳拍档
We make a pretty good team, you know?
像是警界双雄[电影]  福星福将[电影]
Like Starsky and Hutch. Turner and Hooch.
你跟呼哧[福星福将的福星狗]挺像
You do remind me a little of Hooch.
告诉我  小先知
Tell me, seer.
我手里拿的是什么
What do I hold in my hand now?
你拿着
You're holding...
钱包
A wallet.
真令人难以置信  十猜全中
Yes! Incredible. Ten out of ten.
这又是玩哪出
What's going on?
奶奶在教我读心术
Gram's teaching me how to read minds.
她可是天赋过人
And she is a natural.
你这个年纪时可比她差远了
Much better than you were at her age.
我真是感到骄傲
And I'm very proud.
为什么突然对灵异有了兴趣
Why the sudden foray into the mysterious realms?
家族研究课题的作业  一半的任务
It's a genealogy project for school. Half of the assignment
是从家庭成员身上收集故事
is to collect stories from family members.
我居然不知道奶奶的朋友
I had no idea that gram's folks
曾在《康尼岛》中扮演灵异人士
had a mind-reading act on "Coney Island".
他们在风头正劲时可红了
Yeah, they were very famous in their day.
我超喜欢他们的暗语
I love all their codes--
问题中有"告诉我"就表示拿着钱包
How "tell me" means wallet
"透露给我"就表示拿着一对玻璃杯
and "reveal to me" means a pair of glasses.
你秉承的家学渊源  包括你老爸我
Yes, you come from a long line
都是跑江湖卖狗皮膏药的
of hucksters and charlatans, myself included.
但是我们对你还是寄予厚望的
But we have high hopes for you.
一定是贝克特打来的
That must be Beckett.
你怎么知道的
How did you know?
工作日的晚上  现在是十点多了
It's after 10:00 on a weekday.
还会有谁打给你
Who else is it gonna be?
她可真有两下子
Oh, she is good.
非常棒
Brilliant.
我是卡塞尔
Castle.
就知道是你打来的
I knew it was you.
被害人是拉美裔男性  35岁左右
Victim is a hispanic male, mid-30s.
十点半  附近住户溜狗时  发现了尸体
A local spotted him when he was out walking s dog at 10:30.
钱包不见了  如果是劫杀
His wallet's missing. If it was a robbery,
我敢赌上一周的薪水
I bet my week's salary that
凶手不知道他劫的是谁
the killer didn't know who he was rolling.
没钱包里的证件可以确认死者身份吗
You I.D.'ed him without a wallet?
-恐怕是的  -你认识死者吗
- Unfortunately. - You know the guy?
每个纽约人都认识他
Everybody in New York knows the guy.
卡尼奥・维加  棒球选手
Cano Vega, the baseball player.
卡尼奥・维加  你肯定吗
Cano Vega? Are you sure?
在我的梦幻职业球队选秀中
He was my first-round draft pick
他连续三年获首轮选秀权
in my fantasy league three years running.
31.4%的击球率  4只金手套  还有一枚
314 batting average, 4 gold gloves, and one...
冠军戒指
Championship ring.
有一次我差点拿到了他打出的本垒球
I almost caught one of his homers once.
那时他刚从古巴来到美国
He had just came to the States from Cuba,
我爸带我们去希叶球场的露天看台
and my dad took us out to the bleachers over at Shea.
我倒不知道你是个棒球迷
I didn't know you were a baseball fan.
遗传自我老爸
It's genetic, on my dad's side.
我三岁时他就带我去看球
He'been taking me to games since I was 3.
我爸也是
Yeah, mine, too.
卡塞尔  你呢
What about you, Castle?
你爸也迷棒球吗
Your dad a baseball fan?
无可奉告
I really can't say.
世人皆知卡塞尔没爹
Castle is famously fatherless.
-你是被领养的吗  -不是
- What, are you adopted or something? - No.
-那你怎么  -这事儿很复杂
- Then how do you... - It's complicated.
这事儿不复杂
It's not that complicated.
有人用他的头来做挥棒练习
Someone used his head for batting practice.
36盎司的棒球直击后脑
36-ounces to the back of the head.
从血迹来看
By the look of the spatter,
-死者被多次击中  -死亡时间
- he was hit multiple times. - Time of death?
根据尸温  我认为他已死亡两个小时
Uh, from his temperature, I'd say two,
最多三个小时
maybe three hour at the most.
这些伤痕是怎么回事
What's with all this bruising?
死后由棒球击打造成的
Postmortem, from the balls.
发球器在他死亡后  还运转了一段时间
Pitching arm--it ran for a while after he was dead.
像卡尼奥・维加这样的选手
So you'd think a guy like Cano Vega
在自家地下室肯定有击球练习笼
would have a batting cage in his basement.
他这么晚到西班牙裔黑人区
What would he be doing in a sketchy neighborhood
这种穷乡僻壤来做什么
in spanish harlem at this hour of the night?
可能是因为这是他的球场
Maybe because it's Cano Vega field.
附近同事说这是他为社区建的
Local uniforms said that he built it for the community.
想回馈社会
Wanted to give something back.
那么凶手
So our killer
在这里攻击他
hit him from here.
凶手的鞋上沾到了血
And he got blood on his shoe.
让鉴证组过来看看
Have C.S.U. run a sweep.
-看看球场外是否还有血迹  -好的
- See if anything tracked outside of the field. - All right.
看来你的身世和电影
So your dad, what is it,
《妈妈咪呀》(三男一女)如出一辙啊
a "Mamma Mia!" thing?
70年代早期  性爱解放
Early '70s, free love.
我想你老妈在那个年代一定很开放
Yeah, I'll bet your mom was kinda wild back in the day.
你真得需要闭嘴了
You really need to stop talking now.
不好意思  我闭嘴
Sorry. Done.
一个大块头运动员
A big, athletic guy
而且还有2.5英尺长的球棒在手
is swinging a 2-1/2-foot club.
杀他可不容易
He couldn't have been that easy to kill.
除非他完全无心防备
Unless he didn't see it coming.
我谨代表维加的家人
On behalf of the Vega family...
谢谢所有卡尼奥的忠实拥趸
I want to thank all of Cano loyal fans.
感谢你们的爱心与支持
For their love and support.
在这个无比悲痛的时刻
In this time of great sadness,
请大家尊重其家人的隐私
we ask that you please respect his family's privacy.
12年的婚姻了
12 years of marriage.
狗仔们只想从我这里挖边角料
All they want from me is a sound bite.
维加太太  对于你痛失亲人我深表遗憾
I'm very sorry about your loss, Mrs. Vega.
你知道你丈夫昨晚为什么去棒球场吗
Do you know why he'd be in the park last night?
有时他会去那里发泄一下
Sometimes he'd go there to blow off steam,
但晚上从没去过
but never at night.
你知道他昨晚早些时候在哪里吗
Do you know where he was earlier in the evening?
他在我的俱乐部里
He was at my club.
这是贝克特探长  卡塞尔先生
Detective Beckett, Mr. Castle,
这是汤米・泽恩  卡尼奥的老队友
Tommy Zane-- Cano's old teammate.
哪个纽约人
Be hard to be a New Yorker
能不知"货运车"汤米・泽恩啊
and not know "Freight Train" Tommy Zane.
你们有线索吗
So you guys got any leads?
我们正在找  泽恩先生  你说
We're looking into it. Mr. Zane, you said
维加先生昨晚在你的俱乐部里
that Mr. Vega was at your club last night?
我们的俱乐部才对
Our club, actually.
卡尼奥  我  还有几个队友的
Cano and I owned it with a couple of other players.
你记得具体时间吗
Do you know about what time?
大约7点来  7点半离开
Dropped by about 7:00. Left about 7:30.
其实我也没见到他  我陪着一个朋友
I didn't really see him. I was with a friend.
失陪
Excuse me.
维加太太  你知道有没有人
Mrs. Vega, do you know of anyone
想伤害你的丈夫
who would've wanted to hurt your husband?
以前的情况是人人都很喜欢他
Used to be, everybody loved him,
他在古巴移民区特别受欢迎
especially in the Cuban community.
-是什么改变了这点  -古巴之行
- What changed? -The trip.
几个月前
A-a few months ago,
古巴旅游局找上了他
the Cuban Tourism Department approached him.
希望他做古巴旅游业的代言人
They wanted Cano to be the poster boy for the New Cuba.
冒着生命危险逃离了卡斯特罗独裁的古巴
You risk your life to escape Castro's Cuba,
为什么还要回去
why would you go back to visit?
当卡尼奥回去后
While Cano was down there,
古巴当局对待他犹如英雄凯旋  民族英雄
the locals treated him like a hero--their hero.
在官方宴会上  卡斯特罗去了还跟他握手
At a state dinner, Castro came over and shook his hand.
他回来后
When he got home,
他的朋友们说他去了就是叛徒
his friends called him a traitor for going.
说他是菲德尔・卡斯特罗的走狗
Said he was a lapdog for Fidel.
他建棒球场时为他喝彩的人
The same people who cheered when he built that ballpark,
-改口让他去死  -你丈夫有受到恐吓吗
- came up and told him to go to hell. - Did he get any threats?
那是当然了  受到的恐吓数不胜数
You bet he got threats, hundreds of them,
而且都是受阿尔弗雷多・金塔纳的唆摆
and all of them courtesy of Alfredo Quintana.
探长  这是鲍比・福克斯  卡尼奥的经理人
Detective, Bobby Fox, Cano's agent.
很高兴见到你
Nice to meet you.
探长  可以帮忙让那些狗仔带着他们的相机
Detective, could you do something to get those jackals
从维加太太家门前离开吗
and their cameras away from Mrs.Vega's house?
我想想办法
I'll see what I can do.
-谢谢  -谁是阿尔弗雷多・金塔纳
- Thanks. - Who's Alfredo Quintana?
他就是杀害卡尼奥・维加的凶手
He's the guy who killed Cano Vega.
谢谢  卡洛斯
Thanks, Carlos.
阿尔弗雷多・金塔纳
Alfredo Quintana--
法学博士学位  《新希望》报纸的编辑
J.D. PHD and editor of "Una nueva esperanza",
这是由他的基金会发行的报纸
a newspaper published by his foundation,
主要受众是古巴移民社区
primarily for the Cuban community.
这是他两周前的专栏
This is his column from two weeks ago.
卡尼奥必将付出代价
"Cano Vega must pay"?
文章写的是  维加背叛了整个古巴移民区
The article's about how Vega betrayed the Cuban community
他和那个曾经残杀了无数同胞的
by shaking hands with the monster
恶魔刹子手握手了
who butchered thousands of their relatives.
金塔纳宣称  如果维加重投
Quintana says, "If Vega is going to embrace
其曾经逃离的残酷政权的怀抱
"the brutal regime he once escaped,
他将尽己之能唤醒维加对残暴的记忆
he would do well to be reminded of its barbarous cruelty."
听起来就是恐吓啊
Well, that sounds like a threat to me.
我没有恐吓他
I wasn't threatening him.
你让纽约的古巴移民区对他群起而攻之
You turned the local Cuban community against him.
在他对卡斯特罗点头致意时
He turned his back on his people
他就背弃了自己的手足
when he gave Castro his nod of approval.
如果因为他的死  而要我为所写的道歉
If you want me to be sorry about what I wrote because he's dead,
我不会的
I'm not.
我只是写出事实
I wrote the truth.
你确定只是写了一篇文章而已吗
Are you sure that's all you did?
你自己在文章中表明了心迹
You said it yourself in your editorial,
维加必须要付出代价
Vega should pay.
这是个言论自由的国家  不是吗
It's a free country, isn't it?
我有权表达个人观点
I'm entitled to express my opinion.
你的基金组织  古巴人联盟
Your foundation-- Cubans First--
设在98街东段
Is on east 98th street.
那儿离维加的陈尸地点
That's three blocks away
只有三个街区
from the field where Vega's body was found.
你认为我和他的死有关吗
You think I had something to do with his murder?
是的  所谓文字的力量更胜武力
Well, the pen is mightier than the sword.
但是棒球棒也是个不错的选择
But a baseball bat can be pretty effective, too.
昨晚7点到10点你在哪里
Where were you last night between 7:00 and 10:00 p.M.?
我和妻子待在家里
I was at home with my wife.
妻子们总是最好的证明人
Mm. Wives make such convenient alibis.
还有我的儿子们
My sons were there as well...
以及我哥哥
As well as my brother.
有和你没有血缘关系的证明人吗
Do you have anyone who isn't blood related?
比如说公证人之类
A notary, perhaps?
卡尼奥・维加的过错是不可饶恕的
Look, what Cano Vega did is inexcusable.
但我不是凶手
But I am not a murderer.
你确定吗  金塔纳先生
Are you sure about that, Mr. Quintana?
是你煽动整个社区的人反对他
You incited an entire community against him.
在我看来
So from where I'm standing,
你可能不是那个挥棒的人
You might not have swung that bat,
但并不表示你不是凶手
But that doesn't mean that you didn't kill him.
怎么样
Well?
动机很明显  但直觉告诉我不是他
The trigger is out by, but my gut tells me it's not him.
我们需要搜查令
We should get a warrant,
查查他的捐赠人
We'll run his subscribers
看是否有人发恐吓信给死者
against any hate mail that the Vegas might have gotten.
卡塞尔家族没人是警察吗
You sure you got no cop in the Castle family tree?
不  我们家族的人
No, us Castles
都是些玩小把戏的  长官
are mostly con artists and circus folk, Sir.
我想总有几个局里的熟人吧
No, I think there's a little cop in there somewhere.
老实的艺术家吗
Con artists and circus people, huh?
是的  还会读心术
Yep, and mind readers.
真的吗  说说我在想什么
Really? So tell me what I'm thinking.
你在想
You're thi--aah.
You're... You're thinking...
你懒得理我  让我闭嘴
You don't care and you want me to stop talking.
天呐  难以置信
Oh, that's uncanny.
-这是天生的  -贝克特
- It's in the blood. - Yo, Beckett.
-怎么了  -鉴证小组回复说
- Yeah. - Just got back from C.S.U.
他们追踪了球场上凶手鞋底的血迹
They managed to track the blood trail from the killer's shoe
但是在路边就消失了
across the park. It dead-ended at the curb.
看来凶手开车逃跑了
So our killer was driving a car.
是的  而且那地方有泥巴
Yeah. The area was a little muddy,
我们还原了轮胎的部分花纹
So we were able to pull a partial on the tire.
做模型了吗
Any make a model?
比模型还好  轮胎的特征独一无二
Better. The tire marks are distinctive.
上面有两处压力点
They've been ped in two spots.
去年的一起恶性伤人案件中的车
Now those same tire tracks match a car that was tagged
车胎有相同的特征
In an aggravated assault last year.
安东・韦德也是用球棒
The assault was committed with a baseball bat
放高利贷  勒索
By one Anton Wade. Loan sharking, blackmail.
还有一起持致命武器斗殴
Plus assault with a deadly weapon
以及两起伤击案
and two a&b's--
-就是伤人攻击  -我知道
- Assault and battery. - I know.
他是个十足的坏家伙
Right. The guy's one seriously bad dude.
天呐  我突然感觉到些什么了
Whoa! Whoa, whoa, whoa. Oh, I'm sensing something here--
这家伙可能就是凶手
That... This guy might just be our killer.
韦德先生
Mr. Wade,
我们知道你去过棒球场
We have you at the baseball field.
你开车到过犯罪现场
Your car was at the crime scene,
我可不想
Not to mention your unfortunate history
把你用球棒伤人的恶行一一列出
of hitting people with baseball bats.
这些足够送你回监狱了
All of that's enough to send you away.
你可以好好和我们合作  或是保持沉默
So you can play dumb or you can play ball.
这不是开玩笑
Pun intended.
好吧  我到过现场  但是我没有杀他
All right, I was there, but I didn't kill him.
当时他已经死了
He was already dead.
你只是去看看尸体吗
You were just paying the corpse a visit.
他打电话给我  让我去见他
He called and asked me to meet up with him.
当我到那里时  发现大事不妙
And when I got there, I knew how it looked.
所以我立马就走了
So I bounced the hell up outta there.
为什么维加会打电话给你
Why would Vega call you?
他准备还钱给我
He wanted to make a payment on his loan.
以前都是这样的  把钱放在信封里
He always paid the same way, cash in a plain envelope.
我看见信封在他身上  我就拿走了
I saw it on him. I took it.
他是个百万富翁
The guy's a multimillionaire.
而你只不过是个放高利贷的
You're a petty loan shark.
他为什么要向你借钱
What's he doing borrowing money from you?
在我们这行  不说不问才能生存
In my business, you don't ask, you don't tell.
他向你借了多少钱
How much money did he borrow?
他是两周前找我的
He came to me a couple weeks back,
借了20万
Needed 200 grand.
以我的经验看
In my experience...
如果要借那么大一笔钱的话
If you need that kind of coin,
他肯定惹上大麻烦了
He got himself into some real bad... Trouble--
某种杀身之祸
The kind of trouble that gets you killed.
或者是他还不了债
Or maybe he couldn't pay your vig.
你给了他  当头一棒
And you pulled a little "Untouchables" De niro on his head.
如果一个人欠你钱
A guy owing you money?
杀了他可收不回钱  你可以拿他的珠宝
Killing him ain't gonna get you paid. You take his bling,
你可以让他做牛做马
You jack him for his ride,
甚至打碎他的膝盖骨
You maybe even bust his kneecaps.
但他还了尾款
But he made his last installment.
维加信守承诺  我们两清了
Vega made his vig. We were good.
维加的妻子根本不知道借钱的事
Vega's wife didn't know anything about the 200 grand.
真是怪了去了
It doesn't make sense.
以卡尼奥・维加的条件
With his assets, a guy like Cano Vega
他可以向纽约任何一家银行贷款
could get a loan from any bank in New York city.
他为什么要借20万的高利贷呢
So why go to a loan shark for $200,000?
可能银行贷款太花时间
Because bank loans take time.
放高利贷的能马上给钱
Loan sharks give it to you right away.
可能他急需用钱
Maybe he needed the money fast.
或者他不想引人注目
Maybe he needed it kept quiet.
借高利贷不需要办手续和信贷审核
Loan sharks don't require paperwork, credit checks.
或许他不想让妻子知道
Maybe he didn't want his wife to know.
维加也不想让妻子
Vega didn't want his wife
知道他去古巴的原因
to know why he was going to Cuba either.
你认为借钱和那趟旅行有关吗
So you think his trip and the money are related?
是的  他回来一周后
Well, a week after he gets back,
突然就急需20万
He suddenly needs $200,000?
理所当然  两者是有关系的
It stands to reason that the two were connected somehow.
我们刚搜查了韦德的公寓
We just finished a search of Wade's apartment.
发现了部分相同的鞋印
We found a match to the partial shoe print.
但奇怪的是
Yeah, but here's the weird thing--
鞋底的血迹是吻合的
It tested positive for blood on the sole,
但是鞋上的血却不吻合
But negative for blood on the rest of the shoe
清洁剂也不相同
And negative for cleaning agents.
如果韦德杀了维加
If Wade killed Vega,
他鞋子会沾满血迹
Then his shoe would've been covered in blood.
所以韦德说的是实话
So Wade's telling the truth.
他在凶手走后出现
He shows up after the murder,
踩到了血迹走出公园
Tracks some blood outside of the park.
而真正的凶手鞋面上有血迹
While the real murderer gets blood on top of his shoe
但几乎没有留下足迹
And leaves little or no trail behind.
我们查查维加从古巴回来后
Let's find out why Vega comes back from Cuba
-为什么急需那笔钱  -好的
- And suddenly needs 200 grand. - Okay.
你想从哪着手
So where do you want to start?
你们去查查维加的经济情况
You guys look into Vega's financials.
看看我们遗漏了什么
See if we missed anything.
我和卡塞尔从古巴查起
Castle and I will start with Cuba.
古巴  不错啊
Cuba. Good idea.
我喝着甘蔗酒  你就裹着沙滩巾
I'll bring the mojitos. You get the beach towels.
不知道行不行  卡塞尔
Oh, I don't know, Castle.
让我穿着泳装在烈日下暴晒吗
Me in a swimsuit under the hot, blistering sun?
我很乐意给你擦防晒霜
I'd be happy to rub lotion on you.
好了  我还是想些
That's okay. I was actually thinking
比较实际的东西
of something a little bit more local...
比如安排古巴之行的人
Like the man who arranged the entire trip to Cuba.
鲍比・福克斯  他的经纪人
Bobby Fox, his agent.
不错的想法
That's a good idea.
我还是会履行帮涂防晒霜的诺言
But the lotion offer still stands.
不用了  谢谢
No, thank you.
我的手可是很巧的
I have very soft hands.
什么才是职业运动
What is it with professional sports?
我是说  连经纪人都注射类固醇
I mean, even the agencies are on steroids.
福克斯的手上
Fox's client list
可都是名副其实的超级体育明星
is a veritable who's who of star athletes.
每笔合同和薪水都抽百分之五
5% of their endorsements and salaries--
他买得起半个曼哈顿区
You could pay for half of lower Manhattan.
你刚用了"名副其实"这个词吗
Did you just use the word "Veritable"?
是的
Yes, I did.
很性感嘛
Sexy.
你该听听我说"荒谬至极"
You should hear me say "Fallacious."
鲍比・福克斯经纪公司
Bobby Fox agency.
请稍等  有什么能效劳吗
Please hold. Can I help you?
-我要见福克斯先生  -你有预约吗
- I need to see Mr. Fox. - Do you have an appointment?
-我想他能挤出时间的  -是里克吗
- I think he can squeeze me in. - Rick?
-里克・卡塞尔  -你好  队长
- Rick Castle? - Hey, skipper.
自从上次大行动之后都没见过你
I have not seen you since the big move.
-最近怎么样  乔  -糟糕极了
- How are you, Joe? - Pretty awful.
真不敢相信维加走了
I just can't believe this whole Vega thing.
我理解
I know.
令人悲伤啊  你们又是好友  我很抱歉
It's sad. And you two were friends. I'm--I'm sorry.
是啊  他是个伟大的小伙
Yeah, he was a great kid.
他本可成为古巴裔罗伯托・克里米提[拉美裔传奇球员]
Uh, he had the ability to be a Cuban Roberto Clemente.
真是让人心痛
It's just been very sad.
我们来就是想和福克斯先生谈谈
We're actually here to talk to Mr. Fox about it.
-这是凯特・贝克特探长  -你好
- This is detective Kate Beckett. - Hi.
贝克特  凯特  探长
Beckett... Kate... Detective.
谢谢
Thank you.
很高兴认识你
Very nice meeting you. Okay.
祝你们好运
Well, good luck on the case.
我也会帮你们祈祷的
And, uh, I'll say a prayer for you guys.
谢了
Thanks.
别忘了  代我跟你母亲问好
By the way, say hi to your mom for me, okay?
-我会的  乔  -好的
- Will do, Joe.  - Okay.
保持冷静
Smooth.
那个竟然是乔・托利
That was Joe-freakin'-Torre.
我得马上告诉老爸
I gotta call my dad.
办公室在
The office is over...
办公室应该在
The off--his office is...
卡尼奥是个好人
He was a good guy--Cano.
他建球场是为了回馈社会
He built that field because he wanted to give back.
也正因此才会去古巴
I think that's why he went to cuba.
他想证明自己能造福社会
He wanted to see if he could do something good.
不过我想现实总是事与愿违
But I guess things hadn't changed as much as he had hoped for.
发生了什么
What happened?
他在哈瓦那待了一段时间
He had spent some time in Havana with the people.
回来时心烦意乱  还告诉我
He came back pretty upset, and he told me
让我把签约金退给古巴旅游局
To give the tourism guys back their signing bonus.
那可是我第一次让客人退款
First time I ever let a client give money back.
后来我明白了
But I figured, you know,
卡尼奥反对军事独裁
Cano was reneging on a military dictatorship.
但你可不想惹毛这群人
These are not the people you want angry at you,
尤其是已经在18年前成功出逃了
Especially having defected from them 18 years ago.
他曾冒着生命危险逃跑
He risked his life to leave.
你为何又想让他成为新古巴的代言人
Why would you want him to be the poster boy for the new cuba?
我没有  是他自己想回去
Oh, I didn't. I was just as surprised as anyone
我和其他人一样惊讶
That he wanted to do it.
还是我千辛万苦把他带出来
After everything I did to get him out back then?
-你听说了吗  -没有
- Have you heard this story? - No.
你会喜欢这个故事的  卡塞尔
You're gonna like this, Castle.
就像你的推理小说
It's like one of your books.
92年奥运会时
It was the '92 olympics.
古巴在巴塞罗那拿了金牌
The Cubans had just won gold in Barcelona,
都是卡尼奥的功劳
Thanks mostly to Cano.
所以我想让他到美国来
And I wanted to get him to the states
在大联盟里打球
To play in the bigs.
说服他并不难
Now convincing him was the easy part.
难就难在让他登上我的飞机
Getting him onto my plane, that was the hard part.
躲过教练和保镖的视线  终于
We had to get past coaches and minders and finally...
碰到了大章鱼[古巴语]
El pulpo,
那个国土安全局局长
Head of state security,
他的触须控制着所有人
Because he had his tentacles around everybody.
我们还以为能顺利回国  突然
And just as we thought we were home free--boom!
遇到了大章鱼
El pulpo.
我们被抓住了  糟透了
We were caught, sunk.
绝不是开玩笑  当时有支死刑行刑队
A firing squad, I kid you not,
就在哈瓦那等着卡尼奥回去受刑
Was waiting for that kid back in Havana.
知道怎样解决大章鱼的吗
You know how I got us past el pulpo?
劳力士
Rolex.
我把金灿灿的全新劳力士手表给了他
I gave him my shiny new rolex,
他就把头转到一边去了
And he just looked the other way.
这就说明
just goes to show you,
社会主义只是资本主义的伪装罢了
Every socialist is a capitalist when backs are turned.
他接受那份工作会是因为急需用钱吗
Is it possible that he took the Cuba job because he needed the ney?
有这个可能
Well, it's possible, yes.
天知道这些人是怎么挥霍的
God knows those guys know how to blow through money.
而且  他和汤米的那家俱乐部
and plus, he has that club with Tommy
根本就是赔本买卖
That's just a money pit.
古巴那边的工作安排
So in regards to the Cuba job,
还有谁和他同行
Who else went on this trip?
有一些低级别的古巴外交人员
Well, a couple of low-level Cuban diplomats.
我让辛西娅给你张名单
I'll have, uh, Cynthia get you a list.
到底他为什么要去古巴
So what made him go to cuba
又是什么改变了他的主意
And then what made him change his mind?
可能维加为国土安全部工作
Well, maybe Vega worked for the state department.
被派去那里  在和菲德尔・卡斯特罗握手时
Maybe he was sent to shake hands with Fidel
暗中将生物毒素注入他体内
In a secret attempt to release a biotoxin into his system.
俄罗斯人就用放射钋喷射日本寿司
Well, the russians sprayed sushi with radioactive polonium.
还有什么更不靠谱的呢
What-- what's more farfetched?
我都见到了乔・托利  没什么不可能的
Well, I just met Joe Torre, so I guess anything's possible.
贝克特  和预期一样  死因是脑出血
Beckett. Cause of death was cerebral hemorrhaging, as expected.
根据击打的角度推算
Any way to estimate the height of the attacker
-有办法推断凶手的身高吗  -通常可以
- Based on the angle of the blows? - Normally, yes,
但是本案中  凶手第一次的击打部位
But I-in this case, your attacker's first swing
-在头部以下的位置  -有多下面
- Landed a little south of his head. - How far south?
足以让他变性的部位
E-enough to make him a soprano.
该给他颁个精准奖杯
Ow. Shoulda worn a cup.
膝盖骨的撕裂伤表明  维加头部受击打时
Lacerations around the patella suggest Mr. Vega was on his knees
是跪在地上的
When he was hit on the head.
这么说凶手可以是任何人
So our attacker could've been anyone?
男性  女性甚至是儿童
Man, woman or child.
但这不是我叫你们来的原因
But that's not why I called.
在所有新的伤痕中
Among all the fresh bruising,
我发现有几处严重的皮下瘀伤
We also found significant subdermal bruises
这些都不是新伤
That weren't quite as fresh.
伤痕都有拳头大小
The contusions were all fist sized.
他跟人打过架
He was in a fight.
遇害的前几天
Couple days ago.
这个是什么东西的形状
What's this shape right here?
打他的人带着戒指
He was wearing a ring.
不是普通戒指
Not just any ring.
是枚总冠军戒指
A championship ring.
左手无名指
Left-hand ring finger,
正像他的前队友汤米・泽恩
Just like his old teammate, free train Tommy Zane.
妈妈一家的家谱能追溯五月花号时代
You know, mom's family goes all the way back to the "Mayflower."
她的被害妄想症是遗传的吗
What, her persecution complex is genetic?
我也遗传了她的基因
Hey, those are my genes you're talking about,too.
从好的方面来看
Well, look on the bright side.
现在你知道自己遗传了这一倾向
Now that you know you're genetically predisposed,
你可以尽早治疗  以防以后发作
You can seek early treatment, prevent future outbreaks.
你不觉得困扰吗
Doesn't it bother you
不知道自己的父亲是谁
That you don't know who your dad is?
不困扰
No.
为什么这么问  你觉得困扰吗
Why, does it bother you?
是这样的  这个族谱
It's like... I have this family tree,
有一大块是缺失的
And there's a whole chunk of it missing.
我的历史有很长一段根本不曾存在
There's a whole part of my history that doesn't even exist.
奶奶怎么可能不知道
I mean, really, how could gram not know?
我大一时  一次去参加派对
My first year of college, I, uh, went to a party,
遇见一个叫艾莉森的女孩
Met this girl--Allison.
在短暂的六小时里
In the space of six hours,
我们相识  相知  共舞
we met, we talked, we danced,
我们坠入爱河
We fell in love.
但是第二天早上  她消失了
The next morning, she was gone.
我花了整整一年的时间寻找她
I spent a year trying to find her,
我甚至都不知道她姓什么
But I never learned her last name.
那时我没有一天不想念她
There's not a week that goes by I don't think about her.
你奶奶告诉我在遇见他的那晚
Your gram told me that she loved a lifetime
她倾注了此生所有的爱
The night she met him.
但是不知道他是谁  你不觉得遗憾吗
Don't you feel like you're missing out, not knowing?
不  不  这就是神秘的美感
No. Oh, no. That's the beauty of the mystery.
现在我父亲可以是个宇航员
Right now, my father could be an astronaut,
海盗  慈善家  甚至是诺贝尔奖得主
A pirate, a humanitarian, winner of the nobel prize.
有谁比得上这个想象中的父亲呢
I mean, what one man could live up to all that?
他也会拿着罐头吃生奶油吗
You think he ate whipped cream out of a can?
没错  因为是他发明了生奶油
Yes, and he invented whipped cream.
爸爸
Dad!
你会吃不下晚餐的
You're gonna spoil your dinner.
-这就是我的晚餐  -不是
- This is my dinner. - No.
泽恩先生
Mr. Zane.
贝克特探长
Detective Beckett.
卡塞尔先生
Mr. Castle.
泽恩先生  您今晚兴致真好啊
You're in a festive mood tonight, Mr. Zane.
-在悼念亡友吗  - 庆祝美好生活
- Honoring the dead? - Celebrating a life...
用卡尼奥喜欢的方式庆祝生活
The way Cano would've wanted it.
没错  没什么比苹果马提尼更能表达悲伤了
Yes, nothing says "I'm grieving" like an appletini.
泽恩先生  你肯定是个不记仇的人
You must be the "Forgive and forget" type, Mr. Zane,
特别是几天前
Especially after that beating
你狠狠揍了卡尼奥一顿  现在就忘了
That you gave Cano a couple of nights ago.
你在胡说什么
What are you talking about?
维加身上有你留下的多处瘀伤
We found the bruises left on Vega's body from where you hit him,
还包括你的总冠军戒指留下的印记
Including the imprints left by your championship ring.
有25个人有这枚戒指
25 guys have this ring.
他们都把戒指戴在左手无名指吗
Do they all wear it on their left-hand ring finger?
有几个
Some of 'em, yeah.
他们的手上都有
Do they all have abrasions on that finger
对得上号的瘀伤吗
That are consistent with assault?
泽恩先生  到底发生了什么
What happened, Mr. Zane?
卡尼奥是不是要从俱乐部撤资
Was Cano tired of dumping money into this club?
-他关心的不是钱  -那是什么
- He didn't care about the money.  - Then what was it?
他妻子
His wife.
他妻子  你和她
His wife? You and she were--
没有
No.
但是他以为我们
But he thought w--
玛吉很不难过  她认为
Maggie was upset, said she thought Cano
卡尼奥有婚外情  想了解清楚
Was having an affair and wanted to know
问我是否看见他和别人在此约会
If I'd seen him down here at the club with anybody.
你怎么告诉她的
What'd you tell her?
-我跟她说没有   -你说的是真话吗
- I told her no, of course.  - Was that the truth?
以前也有过类似情况
Look, I've been through this before.
卡尼奥只是逢场作戏
Cano was hing some kind of crisis.
他是不会离开她的
He wasn't gonna leave her.
没必要告诉她真相
So why tell her the truth?
这么说维加确实有婚外情
So Vega was having an affair?
跟一个年轻古巴女孩子
I'd seen him with a girl-- young, cuban.
我是后来才发现的  他经常不回家
You know, I figured after his visit, he was missing home.
那晚他见我从他家里出来
Anyway, he saw me leaving his house that night,
他问玛吉为什么我在
And when he asked Maggie why I was there,
她言辞闪烁
she got evasive.
自然的  他认为她也有婚外情
So naturally, he thought she was having an affair of her own.
他来找我算帐
Came after me swinging.
我给了他肋骨几拳
Took a couple of shots to his ribs
让他安静下来听我解释
to calm him down enough before I could tell him the truth.
他约会的姑娘
This girl that he was dating,
-还记得她的名字吗  -不  他没跟我说过
- do you remember her name? - No, he never told me her name.
不过我手机里可能有张照片
But I might have a picture on my phone.
跟职业运动员和政客在一起会怎样
What is it with professional athletes and politicians
他们就是没法不动邪念吗
that they just can't keep it in their pants?
只是自我感觉良好  发育过度的青少年
They're just overgrown teenagers with delicate little egos.
没那么深奥  是简单的算术
It's not that deep. It's just simple math.
他们有更多机会
They just have more opportunity.
你是说  男人是狗
Well, what are you saying, men are dogs?
不  机会越大  可能性就越大
No. The greater the opportunity, the greater the likelihood.
意味着你们两个没什么好担心的
Which means the two of you have nothing to worry about.
莱恩没什么好担心的
Ryan has nothing to worry about.
卡尼奥・维加  另一方面...
Hey. Cano Vega, on the other hand...
他妻子说  他从古巴回来性情大变
His wife said that he changed when he got back from Cuba.
或许不是因为古巴  是因为那个姑娘
Maybe it wasn't Cuba. Maybe it was the girl.
这就能解释那二十万美元了
That could explain the 200 grand.
或许是那姑娘需要这笔钱
Maybe he needed it for the girl.
没有找到她  为何他要
And why he needed to borrow money from a loan shark
-向高利贷借钱  -但玛吉・维加知道了
- without her finding out. - But Maggie Vega did find out.
于是  她决定不再忍受
So she decides she's not gonna take it anymore.
考虑离婚
She considers divorce,
可又想到没完没了的调查
But thought about the endless hours of scrutiny,
媒体上的公开丑闻
the public humiliation in the media.
而且她只能分到一半财产
Not to mention that she'd only get half.
假设没有婚前协议的话
Uh, assuming there's no prenup.
如果她杀死了丈夫  就能得到一切
But if she kills him, she gets everything.
她知道他要去哪里
Mm-hmm. She knows where he's gonna be,
晚上  一个人
Alone, at night.
她去了那里
She goes there.
他信任妻子  放松了警惕
He trusts her, lets his guard down.
她靠近了
She moves in close.
微笑着  捡起棒球棍
She smiles, picks up a bat,
想着他对自己所做的一切
Thinks of everything that he's done to her,
从家庭幸福开始
Starts with the family jewels
以家庭财富而告终
And ends with the family fortune.
胡扯八道  我为什么要谋杀亲夫
This is crazy. Why would I kill my husband?
因为你觉得他有婚外情
Because you thought he was having an affair.
你们知道了
You know?
-怎么知道的  -别管我们怎么知道的
- How? - It doesn't matter how we know.
-重点是你没告诉我们  -这是我和卡尼奥的
- What matters is that you didn't tell us. - It was a private matter
-个人隐私  -也是动机
- between Cano and me. - It's also motive.
维加夫人  你丈夫遇害当晚
Mrs. Vega, where were you on the night
-你在哪里  -一个人在家
- of your husband's murder? - At home alone.
如果你想  可以看监控录像
You can check the security tapes if you want.
那么...  那是真的
So... It's true then?
他有外遇了吗
He was seeing someone else?
我们还不能肯定
We don't know that for sure.
我能肯定
I do.
他爱上了这个女人
He was in love with her.
她叫莱拉
Her name is Lara.
米・卡利妮奥  意思是"我的至爱"
Mi Carinio. It means "My love."
她是谁  不知道
Who is she? I don't know.
为了找线索我把房子翻了个遍
I've torn this house upside down looking for a clue.
唯一找到的就是这张字条
That note is the only thing I've found.
2月16号  遇害的两天前
"2/16"--that's the day before the murder.
他那天进城的  直到十点半才回家
He went into the city that day, didn't get home until 10:30.
所以我知道
That's why I knew.
维加夫人  这个女人很可能涉嫌
Mrs. Vega, this woman is possibly involved
你丈夫的谋杀
in your husband's murder.
之前为何不告诉我们
Why didn't you tell us this before?
因为我...
Because I...
我不希望这是真的
I just didn't want it to be true.
家庭监控录像证明了维加夫人的话
Home security videos confirm Mrs. Vega's story,
汤米・泽恩家的血样  鉴定组测试不符
And C.S.U. Tested negative for blood at Tommy Zane's place.
那个姑娘查得怎么样了
Where are we on the girl?
刚搜索完维加的互联网记录
Just finished combing through Vega's internet records.
不管电邮还是网络通讯
There are no I.M.S, e-mails
他跟莱拉没有任何形式的联系
connecting him in any way, shape or form to a Lara.
电话调查也一无所获
Phones are a dead end, too.
过去两个月里  他并没有
No one who called or was called by Vega in the last two months
和某个莱拉通过电话
Remembers him mentioning anyone named Lara
这个家伙如果是恋爱了
Well, for a guy who's supposedly in love,
跟姑娘可是没保持密切联系
He doesn't do a very good job keeping in touch with his girl.
有的人要绝望了  亲爱的
Some guys are just hopeless. Hey, honey.
是啊  想你了  觉得该给你打个电话
Yeah, I was just thinking about you, thought I'd call you.
只想告诉你我想你了
Well, I just wanted to call to say I miss you.
-是啊  -有的人真可悲
- Yeah. - Some guys are just pathetic.
别妒忌  他还是喜欢你的
Don't be jealous. He still loves you.
维加死前一天见过她
Vega met with her the day before he died,
把照片发到所有辖区
So let's put photos out to all precincts
让同事们详细调查球场周围的区域
And have uniforms canvass the area around the field.
-说不定案发当晚有人见过她  -贝克特
- Maybe somebody saw her the night that he was killed. - Beckett.
-是  长官  -古巴方面查得怎么样了
- Yes, sir. - How we doing on the Cuba angle?
还没有进展  怎么了
Nothinyet. Why?
刚接到新泽西州尤尼恩市警局的电话
Just got a call from the lieu over in Union City, New Jersey.
维加曾在小哈瓦那区的餐馆
Vega was involved in a shouting match
跟他们的一个老主顾争吵
at a restaurant in little Havana with one of their regulars.
然后报警叫警察来劝架
Apparently the cops were called in to break it up.
为何没有事件报告
Why wasn't there an incident report?
那时候警察应古巴领事馆的请求
Cops kept it quiet at the time at the request
-保持沉默  -因为维加
- of the Cuba consulate. -Because of Vega?
不  是因为跟维加争吵的人
No, because of who Vega was fighting with.
马里奥・桑切兹   驻纽约古巴大使馆负责人
Mario Sanchez--head of the Cuba consulate in New York.
他是带维加去古巴的外交官之一
He was one of the diplomats that took Vega to Cuba.
他们吵什么
What did they fight about?
不知道  既然他们一起去了古巴
I don't know, but seeing that they were in Cuba together,
我建议你们去查个究竟
I suggest you find out.
17号晚上  我在大使馆
On the night of the 17th, I was here at the consulate.
你们不会以为我杀了卡尼奥・维加吧
You don't really think I killed Cano Vega, do you?
考虑到他在古巴改变心意  无法想象
Given his change of heart in Cuba, I can't imagine
你们俩曾是最好的朋友
that the two of you were the best of friends.
纽约的这些古巴移民
You could say the same thing
也还不是如此
about most of the Cuban community here.
是的  可有多少人是跟你在餐馆
Yes, but how many of them ended up dead
争吵后以死亡告终的
After fighting with you in a restaurant?
我在忙自己的事
I was minding my own business.
-维加才是挑起事端的人  -为什么
- Vega was the one who decided to pick a fight with me. - Why?
我负责他在古巴的行程
I was in charge of his schedule in Cuba.
我猜他可能不喜欢被牵着鼻子走吧
I guess he didn't like to be told what to do or where to go.
听起来像是你给他拴了条链子
Sounds like you kept him on a pretty tight leash.
我们一反常态
We did a counterrevolutionary the courtesy
礼貌的允许他进入我们的国土
of allowing him back on our soil.
我们可不想让他四处闲逛
We weren't about to just let him wander around.
你比任何人都清楚
So you would know better than anyone else
-维加旅行时做过什么  -那是我的工作
- What Vega did on his trip? - That's my job.
我们问过的每个人都说
Everyone we've spoke to about Vega
维加从古巴回来性情大变
Says he came back from Cuba a different man.
他在那里到底出了什么事
What happened to him down there?
他很激动
he was very emotional
他在那里的所有时间
The whole time he was there--
都在跟当地人交谈  对他们感到抱歉
Uh, talking to the locals, feeling sorry for them
为他们的穷困和自己的富有
Because they were poor and he was rich.
事实是  他有负罪感
Truth is, he felt guilty.
当维加回来后  借了二十万现金
When returned, he borrowed $200,000 in cash.
有可能
Is it possible
他想给这个岛集资
that he was trying to funnel money to the island,
-帮助一些当地人吗  -我不知道
-Help some of the locals out, maybe? -Not on my watch.
是啊  你无法掌控
Yeah, you can't have that.
有钱人分享他们的财富  很像社会主义
Rich people sharing their wealth? That's like socialism.
得了吧
Please.
事实是正像美国人  卡尼奥・维加被惯坏了
The truth is that Cano Vega, like all Americans, was spoiled.
当他眼前出现贫瘠时
When the poverty was before his eyes--
是无法形容的悲惨
It's an unspeakable tragedy.
然而  眼不见心不烦
And then, out of sight, out of mind.
他不知道我有所觉察
He didn't know that I was aware,
你们想知道
But do you want to know
维加最关心古巴的什么事情吗
the thing that interested Vega most about Cuba?
一个姑娘
A girl.
什么姑娘
What girl?
他见过很多当地人  吻过很多孩子
He met a lot of locals, kissed a lot of babies.
我只能假设他在岛内旅游时
I can only assume it was a pretty young thing
遇到一个漂亮的姑娘
He met while he was touring the island.
知道她的名字吗
Do you know her name?
莱拉
Lara.
她名叫莱拉
Her name was Lara.
维加在古巴爱上了一个姑娘
So Vega fell in love with a girl in Cuba.
如果你相信桑切兹说的话
If you take Sanchez's word.
他不可能凭空说出莱拉这名字
Well, he couldn't have just pulled the name Lara out of thin air.
根据他妻子找到的字条
According to the note that the wife found,
维加在遇害前一晚和莱拉应该见过面
Vega and Lara were supposed to meet the night before he was murdered.
如果她在古巴
Now how are they supposed to do that
-他们怎么见面  -如果她在岛上
-if she's stuck in Cuba? -If she's stuck on the island,
怎么会跟维加在俱乐部照相
How did she end up in that photo with Vega at his club?
肯定有个理由能解释一切
There has to be an explanation that makes this all make sense.
有  照片里站在维加旁的不是莱拉
There is. The woman standing next to Vega in the picture is not Lara.
维加被杀的棒球场附近  有居民认出了她
A resident near the ballpark where Vega was killed I.D.'ed her.
她叫阿娜  阿娜・蕾维拉
Her names Ana, Ana Rivera.
她是社区俱乐部的服务生
She's a waitress in the neighborhood.
同事正把她带过来
Uniforms are bringing her in now.
她和维加有什么关系
What's her connection to Vega?
古巴  半年前她从古巴逃来纽约
Cuba. She escaped six months ago.
我工作的酒吧和他的球场很近
We met at a bar where I work,
我们就在那里认识的
near his field.
他听说我去年才从古巴过来
He heard I'd just come over from Cuba last year,
就请我出去喝几杯
and he invited me out for drinks.
你知道他已婚吗
Did you know he was married?
我们不是那种关系
It wasn'like that.
他只想聊天  聊家乡
He just wanted to talk... about home.
他想家  我觉得因此他才回了古巴
He missed it. I think that's why he wanted to go.
他从古巴回来后与你合影
You were photographed with him after the trip.
那时他也仅仅只想聊天吗
Did he still want to... just talk?
是的  他想知道我是怎么
Yes. He wanted to talk about
从古巴来到这里的
my trip here from Cuba.
不是爱上我  只为知道我是怎么出境的
It was like he was obsessed. He wanted to know how I got out.
你对他怎么说的
And what did you tell him?
阿娜  你对维加先生怎么说的
Ana, what did you tell Mr. Vega?
我说我家人认识一个熟人
I said my family knew a man.
只要你给得起钱
If--if you pay him lots of money,
米・卡利妮奥就能带你去美国
Mi Carinio comes and takes you to America.
米・卡利妮奥是什么
Mi Carinio?
他的船
His boat.
人先坐船到牙买加
It takes you to Jamaica,
然后再坐飞机到美国
and then you fly to America.
入境一定要乘飞机  因为如果乘船
It's important that you fly, because if you come by boat,
他们就会把你遣送回国
then they can send you back.
这是海路陆路入境政策
That's the wet-foot, dry-foot policy.
维加在想办法让新女友离开古巴
Vega was looking for a way to get his new girlfriend out of Cuba.
米・卡利妮奥  2月16日  下午八点半
"Mi Carinio ," 2/16, 8:30 p.m.
他似乎成功了
It looks like he succeeded.
米・卡利妮奥  2月16日到达牙买加
"Mi Carinio" to Jamaica 2/16,
这意味着她17日到达
which means she arrived on the 17th.
恰好是维加遇害当天 这不是巧合
That's the same day Vega died. That can't be a coincidence.
阿娜  你告诉了维加先生如何联系
Ana, you told Mr. Vega how to get in touch
帮你离开古巴的人吗
with the man who got you out of Cuba.
是的  他主编一份报纸
Yes. He runs a newspaper.
《新希望》报纸  在98街东段
"Una nueva esperanza," on East 98th.
主编是阿尔弗雷多・金塔纳吗
Alfredo Quintana, the editor?
他对我们撒谎了
He lied to us.
一开始你们指控我谋杀维加
All right, first you accuse me of killing Vega.
后来你们又说我在帮他
Then you're saying that I'm helping him.
也许你们先该想到清楚明白
So maybe you guys should make up your mind.
事实上  我们一看到你账户上
Well, actually, we made up our minds
那二十万就清楚明白了
once we saw the $200,000 in your bank account.
卡尼奥・维加向高利贷借就是这个数目
That's the exact amount Cano Vega borrowed from a loan shark.
因为你们在做违法勾当
Since what you were doing was illegal,
所以他不想留下证据
he didn't want there to be any record of it.
我不明白你在说什么
You know, I don't know what you're talking about.
这些不是我的账户
These aren't my accounts.
这是基金会的账户
This is the foundation's account.
上面甚至没有我的名字
My name isn't even on them.
这就是你把赃款藏于其中的原因
Which is why you hid the money there,
让我们更难找到
to make it harder for us to find.
这些是慈善捐款
These were charitable contributions.
那个女孩在哪里
Where's the girl?
什么女孩
What girl?
金塔纳先生  你和你的基金会
Mr. Quintana, you and your foundation
将面临偷运人口的指控
are facing human smuggling charges.
你希望再加上妨碍司法公正
Do you really want me to add obstruction of justice
援助和教唆谋杀罪吗
and aiding and abetting a murderer to that?
你喜欢出版事业  对吧
You like the press, don't you?
那喜欢涉嫌谋杀卡尼奥・维加吗
How are you gonna like being linked to Cano Vega's murder?
你知道他们会怎么想吗
You know what they'll see?
我从卡斯特罗的独裁下拯救了一个女孩
That I saved a girl from under Castro's regime.
收费的
For a price.
我本打算免费的
Yeah, I would've done it for free.
但你没有
Yeah, but you didn't.
你真的准备把下半生赌在
Are you really ready to stake your entire future
某个你陌生女孩身上吗
on some girl you don't even know?
维加给她买了一套公寓
Vega had an apartment for her.
她一到美国我就把她带到了那里
I took her there when I got her to the mainland.
-在哪里  -尤尼恩市萨米特大道
- Where? - Union City, Summit Avenue.
纽约警察  纽约警察
Nypd! Nypd! Nypd! Police! Police! Police! Police! Nypd! Nypd!
-没人  -没人
- Clear. - Clear.
屋里似乎没人
Looks like nobody's home.
可怜的女孩需要去宜家买点东西
This girl's in dire need of a trip to Ikea.
这张床从未铺过
This bed hasn't even been made.
我觉得她不住这里
I don't think she was sleeping here.
贝克特
Beckett.
像是泥
Looks like dirt.
让鉴证组过来
Get C.S.U. down here.
大家看
You guys.
这有血迹
There's blood.
绝对是维加的
It's definitely Vega's.
-脚印呢  -那就很难确定了
- And the footprint? - That's harder to nail down.
泥土的成分
The composition of the dirt
和城区各处的泥土都很相似
is pretty similar to dirt anywhere in the city.
所以不能证明她在现场吗
So we can't actually prove that she was at the scene?
我只是说很难确定
I just said it's harder.
但泥土里含有微量二氧化钛
But there were traces of titanium dioxide in the dirt.
-粉笔  -在棒球场上用来画线的
- Chalk. - Like what they use to trace lines on baseball fields.
所以她去了棒球场
So she heads to the field,
用球棒打了维加的头
takes a little batting practice on Vega's head,
回家  收拾东西  然后逃走了
heads home, packs her things, hits the road.
给词组"击跑配合战术"下了新的定义
Giving a whole new meaning to the term "hit-and-run."
贝克特  贝克特
Beckett. B-e-c-k-e double-t.
编号41319
Badge 4-1-3-1-9.
我需要交通安全管理局拦截
I need a T.S.A. hold on
一个可能潜逃的疑犯
a potential fugitive.
好  我不会挂
Yes, I'll hold.
同事在发布金塔纳那给的莱拉的照片
Uniforms are circulating that picture of Lara we got from Quintana.
张贴在她住处方圆1公里内
They're plastering it on every storefront
所有商店中
within a mile of her place.
凶手是那个女孩吗
So it was the girl?
证据都指向她
Evidence looks that way.
我们推测她用美人计使维加帮她离开古巴
We figure she honey trapped Vega into giving her tickets out of Cuba,
她到这里以后
and when she got here,
他想要的她不能给
he wanted a little more than she was willing to give,
祸起萧墙
and things went south from there.
也许从头到尾古巴政府也参与其中
Maybe it was the Cuban government all along.
他们憎恨维加的背叛
They hated Vega for defecting.
所以他们派出美女间谍让他坠入爱河
So they send a beautiful spy for him to fall in love with.
计划奏效了  他把她偷渡回家
It works. He smuggles her back home,
然后突然  他死了
and bam! He's dead.
听起来好像卡塞尔写的小说
Sounds like a Castle story.
我会起名为《最后的列车》[电影]
I'll call it "Coraz de fuego."
我需要拘留令
Yes. I need a detain and contain.
禁止飞行出境协议  谢谢
All no-fly protocols. Thank you.
我们真的应该监视领事馆
Though we really should stake out the consulate.
我们早想到了
Way ahead of you.
一小时前已经开始监视领事馆
Surveillance has been there for about an hour.
如果她不是出于自卫而杀死他
If she killed him out of self-defense,
她会回去找幕后黑手的
then she'd go back to the devil she knows.
我感觉到有人在怀疑我的推测
And yet I'm sensing skepticism on my theory.
-谢谢  -读心者
- Yeah, thanks. - Mind reader.
你们俩都是天才
Well, you're both geniuses.
我们的人在领事馆
That was our guys at the consulate.
他们刚看见莱拉走进大门
They just spotted Lara walking right through the door.
我无可奉告
I don't know what to tell you.
我从没见过这个女孩
I've never seen that girl before.
那你应该买视力矫正镜了
Well,then you should invest in some corrective lenses.
我们的人看见她进来  还不到半小时
Our surveillance team saw her coming in here not half an hour ago.
你们的人  你们现在在监视我们
Surveillance team? You're watching us now?
仅在法律允许的范围之内
Only within the scope of the law.
幕后看客成了被监视的人
The watcher becomes the watched.
我很喜欢用反讽  问她吧
I'm a big fan of irony. Ask her.
她是个要求庇护的古巴公民
She's a Cuban citizen requesting asylum.
她是谋杀案的嫌疑人
She's a suspect in a murder investigation.
你想让我把她交给美国政府吗
And you expect me just to hand her over to the American authorities?
桑切兹先生  我相信你很清楚
Mr. Sanchez, as I'm sure you're well aware,
一个国家的领事和大使馆
a country's consulate and its embassy
享有不同的权力
have a different set of rights and privileges.
这只是领事馆
This is only a consulate.
你并不享有外交豁免权
You do not have diplomatic immunity.
现在就交出那个姑娘
Produce the girl now,
否则我将取得搜查令  并向公众公开
or I will get a search warrant and make a public spectacle
贵国政府在美国国土私藏嫌犯
of your government harboring a criminal on American soil.
不  他不是我杀的
No, I-I-I did not kill him. Please.
-你们相信我  -那你为什么要逃跑
- You have to believe. - Then why did you run?
你为什么想回古巴
Why did you try to go back to Cuba?
我怕那个人也会杀我
I was afraid the man will kill me, too.
-谁  -他遇害当晚来的男人
- What man? - The one who come the night he died.
他来了...el piso[西班牙语]
He come to... El piso.
公寓  他去了公寓
The apartment. He came to the apartment.
有个男人在维加遇害当晚
There was a man who came to the apartment
去了公寓  所以你才逃跑吗
the night that Vega died, and that's why you were running?
他杀害了我父亲
He kill my father.
你父亲
Your father?
维加
Vega.
卡尼奥・维加是你父亲
Cano Vega is your father?
莱拉  让我们从头开始
O-okay, Lara, take us from the beginning.
从头说起[西班牙语]
Desde del principio.
维加和我母亲...
Vega and my mother...
维加出逃前已经和她母亲订婚
Vega and her mother were engaged when he defected.
她本应该一起来的  但却没有
She supposed to come, but she didn't.
作为对维加叛逃的惩罚
As punishment for what Vega did,
他们把她母亲送进了监狱
They threw her mother in prison.
当时她母亲已经怀有身孕
she was pregnant with her at the time.
维加知道这事吗
Did Vega know about this?
直到两个月前
Not until a couple of months ago
他听说原来他有一个女儿
when he heard a rumor that he had a daughter.
维加就是为这事回古巴的
Well, that's why vega went to Cuba.
去证实他到底有没有女儿
To see if he really did have a daughter.
他们并没见着面
They didn't actually meet
因为古巴政府正监视着他
Because the government was watching him.
但他收到了她的信息
But he got her a message
让他尽快救她出去
Saying that he would get her out as soon as he could.
我第一次见我父亲是在三天前
The first time I meet my father was... three nights ago,
当时我就想告诉他
And I want to tell him
他一手酿成了多少痛苦
How much suffering he caused.
她从小到大一直认为
She grew up believing
他父亲为了富贵荣华而抛妻弃子
That her father had abandoned her mother to get rich.
但是他却告诉她  事实并非如此
But he told her that that wasn't true...
他之所以出走  只是因为
That he only defected
她母亲曾答应他一起远走高飞
Because her mother said that she was going to as well.
但她却在最后关头改变了主意
But that she had changed her mind at the last minute.
这些年来
All these years,
他一直以为她已经和自己恩断义绝
He had thought that she had turned her back on him.
但却没想到
He never knew that they--
政府利用他杀鸡儆猴
That the government had made an example of him
震慑其他球员
To all the other players.
他完全不知道她已死于狱中
He never knew that she had died in prison.
我父亲...
My father...
当他从我这里得知这些时  沮丧万分
Is very upset when I tell him this.
他说他需要和某个人谈谈
He said he need to talk to someone.
他给了我一些钱买吃的
He, uh, uh, give me money for food.
然后我就再也没见过他
I never see him again.
你之前说  曾有个男人出现在公寓
You said earlier that there was a man at the apartment.
当时我出去买吃的
When I go to... The market to go buy food,
等我回来的时候
When I come back...
我见到一个男人  出现在公寓
I see a man at the, um, um, apartment,
但并不是我父亲
Not my father.
我当时害怕极了  于是赶紧离开
I was so scared, so I leave.
后来我就听说卡尼奥・维加死了
Then I hear Cano Vega is dead.
于是我躲了起来
So I run, and I hide.
我只想回家
I just wanted to go home.
他杀了我父亲
He killed my father.
这个出现在你公寓的男子
This man who came to your apartment...
你能向我描述他的样子吗
Can you describe him for me?
可以
Yes.
咱们把话说清楚先
Let--let me get this straight.
一个非法偷渡客
An illegal claiming to be
声称自己是卡尼奥・维加的女儿
Cano Vega's daughter,
刚来到这个国家不到24小时
After being in this country for less than 24 hours,
就辨认出一个酷似我的人
Identifies someone who kind of looks like me
而且还是在晚上远距离看到的
From a distance at night?
有没有搞错  二位
Well, gee, guys.
怎么  难道我要现在就签字画押吗
What, do I--what, do I sign my confession right now
还是要先开个新闻发布会
Or after the big, uh, press conference?
现在就开吧
Well, now's good.
拜托  孩子们
Come on, kids.
拜托
Come on.
你们知道他是我朋友
You know he was my friend.
更别提我们签了高额佣金
Not to mention, a hefty commission.
我动机何在
What's my motive?
福克斯先生  有钱人一旦出了问题
The thing about people who have a lot, Mr. Fox,
那一定不是小事
Is that they have the most to lose.
我相信维加得知真相时
I'm sure vega felt betrayed
觉得自己被出卖了
when he learned the truth.
真相  什么真相
The truth? About what?
那个你津津乐道的故事
Your favorite story--
1992年  巴塞罗那奥运会
Barcelona, 1992.
只是你跳过了那部分
Only you left out the part
关于你是如何谎称
Where you lied to Cano Vega
帮卡尼奥・维加的未婚妻逃走的
About helping his fiance defect.
她临时变卦  这又不是我的错
It's not my fault that she changed her mind,
实际上  你没办法带她离开
Truth is, you couldn't get her off the island.
同时  你也知道他宁愿留在那里陪她
But you did know that he'd rather be there with her
也不愿在大满贯赛里帮你赚个盆满钵满
Than here making big bucks for you in the majors.
于是你让他以为她变心了
So you let him believe that she had changed her mind.
同时为了确保他再也无从得知真相
And to keep him from ever finding out the truth,
你把她关了起来
You had her put away.
关起来  还是在古巴  拜托
Put away? In Cuba? Oh, come on.
我的确有很多门路
I-I have a lot of pull,
但是  要想在军事独裁国家说上话
But, uh, influencing a military dictatorship
并不像在马戏团餐厅[名店]订位那么容易
Isn't as easy as getting a dinner reservation at le cirque.
但你确实做到了
You'd influenced their people before.
玛纽埃・古铁兹  花名大章鱼
Manuel gutierrez, A.K.A. El pulpo--
那个大墨鱼
The octopus.
你带着古巴国家队的明星球员跑了
You walked away with the star player
而代价只是一块劳力士
Of the cuban national team for a rolex.
我们调查过了
We did a little research.
在她的审讯中  他是主要目击证人
He was the chief witness at her trial.
指控维加未婚妻
Was denouncing Vega's fiance
也是你和大章鱼计划的一部分吧
Always a part of your plan with el pulpo
还是你得为此额外付费
Or did you have to pay extra for that?
我听说你很擅长和杀手讨价还价
I've heard you're a killer negotiator.
你们不会是认真的吧
You can't possibly be serious.
当维加发现了一切之后
When vega figured out what you had done,
他在俱乐部打电话给你约你见面
He called you from his club and told you to meet him.
我猜他跟踪了你并且威胁要毁了你
I think he came after you and threatened to destroy you
因此你杀了他
And that's why you killed him.
这故事太蹩脚了  孩子们
It's a hell of a story, kids.
我雇大章鱼害死我球员的女人
I paid el pulpo to take care of my player's girl
而且还是在古巴政府
When the Cuban government
眼皮底下顶风作案
is sending away people every day?
这算个什么说法
That's a hell of a tale.
这根本是在凭空臆断
It's pure conjecture.
你想要真凭实据吗
You know what's not conjecture?
我们在你的汽车驾驶座
The blood that we found
脚垫上发现了血迹
On the driver's side floor mat in your car.
属于维加
That was vega's blood.
尽管你小心清理过了
As much as you tried to clean
那双你谋杀维加时穿的
Those $5,000 pair of shoes you were wearing
价值五千大洋的鞋子
While you smashed Vega's skull in,
你还是没弄干净
You didn't quite get all of it.
辛西娅  通知我的律师
Hello, Cynthia. Call my lawyer.
你跟他说  我会支付他一笔
You tell him he's about to earn
前所未有的天价律师费
The outrageous, obscene amounts of money I pay him.
转过身去
Turn around.
转身
罗伯特・福克斯  你因谋杀卡尼奥・维加被捕
Robert fox, you're under arrest for the murder of Cano Vega.
莱拉以后怎么办
what's gonna happen to Lara?
她可以继续留在美国一年
She can stay in the states for a year and then decide
再决定是否加入国籍
whether she wants to apply for citizenship or not.
我不敢想象她留在这里的情形
Oh, I can't imagine her staying.
举目无亲
Her last bit of family is gone.
她唯一认识的人已经死了
I mean, the only person that she knew here is dead.
其实还有一个人
Well, there is one more person
她应该见一下
That she should meet.
你就是莱拉
So you're Lara?
维加先生刚离开古巴  她便出生了
She was born in Cuba right after Mr. Vega defected.
她不是他女朋友
She's not his girlfriend.
-她是他的女儿  -卡尼奥有个女儿
- She's his daughter. - Cano had a daughter?
我父亲他
My father...
不知道你是否愿意我留在这里
Didn't know how you would like to have me here.
他  他有些顾虑
He, uh... He had fear
到底该不该告诉你我的事情
To tell you about me.
没事
It's okay.
她说她父亲深爱着你
She says she knows her father loved you very much,
他并不想伤害你
And he didn't want to hurt you.
她和他都希望
And that she hoped and he hoped that,
你们可以成为一家人
Together, you could be a family.
我家就是你家[西班牙语]
Mi casa es su casa.
谢谢
Thank you.
嗨  老爸
Hey, dad.
嗨  女儿  那么晚了你干嘛呢
Hey, daughter. What are you doing up so late?
等你
Waiting for you.
我又做错什么了
Did I do something wrong?
没有
No.
我只是在想你之前说的关于你爸爸的事
I was just thinking about what you said about your dad,
他可能是任何你所希望的角色--
How he could be anything you imagine him to be--
宇航员  或者海盗
An astronaut or a pirate.
生奶油发明者
Whipped cream inventor.
对  也可能是生奶油发明者
Or whipped cream inventor.
但有一样他一定做不到
But there's one thing he can't be.
-什么  -一个父亲
- What's that? - A dad.
一个普通的爸爸
Just a regular dad,
教他的儿子如何骑车
Teaching his son how to ride a bike
帮他写作业  或者陪他投球
Or helping him with homework or having a catch.
你没经历过这些  我觉得很难过
It makes me sad you didn't get to have those things.
既然我不曾拥有  那也就谈不上失去
Well... I can't miss what I didn't have.
如果你可以拥有呢
What if you could have it?
你在吧台后面藏了台时光机
You have a time machine behind the kitchen counter?
怎么说  乖儿子
What do you say, son
和你老爸投会儿球如何
How about a game of catch with your old man?
好啊  乐意奉陪
Yeah, I'd like that.
很好
Good.
准备好了吗
You ready?
没问题
Ready.